<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>afronski.pl - Tag: elixir-conf-eu</title>
    <description>Random thoughts from top of my head - afronski.pl</description>
    <link>http://www.afronski.pl</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.afronski.pl/tag/elixir-conf-eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Elixir Conf EU 2015 - Afterthoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;elixir-conf-eu-2015---afterthoughts&quot;&gt;Elixir Conf EU 2015 - Afterthoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.afronski.pl/2015/04/06/the-best-of-lambda-days.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; about interesting events, I have said that more of them will come in future. I have participated in one of these - &lt;em&gt;ElixirConf EU&lt;/em&gt; in Kraków and I must admit - it was the best conference I have ever been since &lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyrd.com/2011/falsy-values/&quot;&gt;Falsy Values in 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the second in the world conference about &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; programming language, it brings almost 200 people interested in that topic to the former Polish capital. Most of people was either from &lt;em&gt;Ruby&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; side and I think that such mixture is a &lt;em&gt;key thing&lt;/em&gt; related to the &lt;em&gt;joy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; of that event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ElixirConfEU2015Header.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elixir Conf EU 2015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talks-and-workshops&quot;&gt;Talks and Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a day before actual conference organizers prepared two workshops - one about &lt;em&gt;Phoenix&lt;/em&gt; framework and one about &lt;em&gt;OTP and Elixir&lt;/em&gt;. I have participated in the second one - it was a really nice experience. Workshop was full of knowledge, I have met interesting people, with very positive attitude, whom are willing to network and share their experiences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual conference days was started and ended with very nice keynotes - each of them was a different experience. We have very nice and thoughtful keynote from Joe Armstrong, which explains many problems related to the programming language design, from the perspective of &lt;em&gt;Elixir’s&lt;/em&gt; older brother - &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt;. Jose Valim presented bright future and interesting details related with &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; evolution, and finally Chris had a very nice overview and development plans related with &lt;em&gt;Phoenix&lt;/em&gt; framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I was also impressed by other talks. It was very interesting to see many use cases in which people used that piece of technology. I think that both groups have many valuable opinions and observations. For me, talks made by people with &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; experience were particularly valuable, because they are coming from more mature technology. It is a different background and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atmosphere&quot;&gt;Atmosphere&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to focus on one particular element, which makes this conference so enjoyable - &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. I have never met so many &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;friendly&lt;/em&gt; people. I have wonderful time during networking, countless talks during breaks or lunches. And to sum it up - during lightning talks &lt;em&gt;Jose Valim&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jim Freeze&lt;/em&gt; received a &lt;em&gt;3D printed Elixir logo&lt;/em&gt; designed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hrobeers.github.io/finFoil/&quot;&gt;finFoil&lt;/a&gt; software made by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hrobeers&quot;&gt;@hrobeers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazing community!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center-tweet&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ElixirConfEU&quot;&gt;@ElixirConfEU&lt;/a&gt; Thanks for the great conference. My lightning talk including the Elixir 3D file: &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/m06YLIwA5h&quot;&gt;http://t.co/m06YLIwA5h&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/0VJa9SDN02&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/0VJa9SDN02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Hans Robeers (@hrobeers) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hrobeers/status/591794764351197184&quot;&gt;April 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good choice to invest my time and money in that event. Three days full of &lt;em&gt;energy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; sharing. As a community we have interesting perspectives. We can derive from very experienced and stable &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; ecosystem. We have a very nice and promising community, full of amazing and creative people. I will go definitely to the next &lt;em&gt;ElixirConf EU 2016&lt;/em&gt; which take place in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you there! &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:smile:&quot; alt=&quot;:smile:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f604.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hrobeers/status/591794764351197184&quot;&gt;Lightning talks and their effect, done by @hrobeers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elixirconf.eu/&quot;&gt;Elixir Conf EU 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/2015/05/07/elixir-conf-eu-2015-afterthoughts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/2015/05/07/elixir-conf-eu-2015-afterthoughts.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
