<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>afronski.pl - Tag: pragmatic-programmer</title>
    <description>Random thoughts from top of my head - afronski.pl</description>
    <link>http://www.afronski.pl</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.afronski.pl/tag/pragmatic-programmer/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Books that changed my career - The Pragmatic Programmer</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;books-that-changed-my-career---the-pragmatic-programmer&quot;&gt;Books that changed my career - The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;quote class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;This blog post is a next one in the series which contains the most influential books that I have read in my programming career. This is my private ranking, each post contains a good dose of my private opinions (you have been warned &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;), but besides that I hope that you will find it valuable.&lt;/quote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.afronski.pl/books-that-changed-my-career/2015/03/07/books-that-changed-my-career-pragmatic-thinking-and-learning.html#whats-next&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I have mentioned that I have this book in three copies - two editions of e-book version (Polish and English) and printed Polish translation. The last one is the most valuable for me, because I have received it as a gift from my colleague during studies, with very nice inscription (after graduating 3rd year, if I recall correctly - Hi Rafał! &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to focus in this post on the actual details, because book is well known in the community. And it definitely deserves its &lt;em&gt;fame&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;glory&lt;/em&gt;. It is even more actual, than &lt;em&gt;C Programming Language&lt;/em&gt; by Kernighan and Ritchie. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:stuck_out_tongue_winking_eye:&quot; alt=&quot;:stuck_out_tongue_winking_eye:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f61c.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt; Actually it is a huge foundation under the &lt;em&gt;Agile Manifesto&lt;/em&gt; (it was published two years before formalized meeting happened, where the document was signed), moreover - both authors are signatories of that manifesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer: From Journeyman to Master&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;The Pragmatic Programmer&quot; src=&quot;/assets/PragmaticProgrammer.jpg&quot; class=&quot;book&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;subtitle&quot;&gt;Subtitle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost each science specialization has its own book, which is required to read before you will start a professional career. If you are an apprentice, you will probably get most of this book, because your mind is fresh and knowledge base is relatively small, especially regarding topics like &lt;em&gt;estimation&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;career planning&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;teamwork&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this case, even the subtitle suggests that it is a book for all generations of programmers. Of course younger programmers will benefit the most, but not surprisingly, even the more experienced folks can find this book refreshing. Why? Because it is a classic example of knowledge which is &lt;em&gt;universal&lt;/em&gt;, but sometimes &lt;em&gt;not commonly known&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;forgotten&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;universal-truths&quot;&gt;Universal Truths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to introduce the most favorite advice and guides from the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.artima.com/intv/tracer.html&quot;&gt;Tracer Bullets and Prototypes&lt;/a&gt; - If the second term is well known (maybe even more as a &lt;em&gt;proof of concept&lt;/em&gt;), we often forgot about first one. And that is a huge mistake, because it is highly useful. Moreover, we often want to use the &lt;em&gt;tracer bullets&lt;/em&gt;, but we misuse &lt;em&gt;prototype&lt;/em&gt; instead - building not a &lt;em&gt;walking skeleton&lt;/em&gt;, but a &lt;em&gt;walking dead&lt;/em&gt; project. The main difference is related with the destiny of both - &lt;em&gt;prototype&lt;/em&gt; should be built, conclusions should be gathered and whole project should be thrown out through a window. If we want to build a skeleton and fiddle with the internals, because we do not feel how it should look like right now, we should use a &lt;em&gt;tracer bullet&lt;/em&gt;. And the rules how to build both are different. I encourage you to grab your own copy, look into that chapter and read it out loud (if you do not have one yet - here is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pragprog.com/book/tpp/the-pragmatic-programmer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to an official shop).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_repeat_yourself&quot;&gt;DRY&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it&quot;&gt;YAGNI&lt;/a&gt; and other acronyms - During my career I ran into these abbreviations many times. And book is full of it - it does not mean that it is something wrong. Our industry is full of it - it builds our internal dictionary and sometimes it adds more meaning. Aforementioned two - &lt;em&gt;DRY&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Don’t Repeat Yourself&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;YAGNI&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need It&lt;/em&gt;) are kind of an &lt;em&gt;axioms&lt;/em&gt; which are not negotiable. For a beginner, especially curious one, listening just one word thrown out as an explanation can be infuriating, but eventually we will all learn what it means to violate that rules. In a hard way. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boiling_frog&quot;&gt;Boiling frog&lt;/a&gt; - Typical metaphor for a problem, which can be observed from the outside, but never from the inside. It affects our health in the long run, it changes our attitude and forms the future career. Sometimes it is more healthier to step out for a while and just listen, observe our/team/project behavior. Practice makes permanent and our little habits can grow to an overwhelming problems in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor&quot;&gt;Bus factor&lt;/a&gt; - My personal favorite, mostly because I was once such person and I will not lead to that situation again. I really like the &lt;em&gt;Agile&lt;/em&gt; attitude about cross-functional teams because it helps solve the problem. Your team should be resilient to a situation, when you are losing one person from the team. And you as a &lt;em&gt;responsible&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;professional&lt;/em&gt; software engineer should not add anything to such problematic factor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging&quot;&gt;Rubber Duck Debugging&lt;/a&gt; - This is probably the most known advice from the book. Mostly because our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.afronski.pl/books-that-changed-my-career/2015/03/07/books-that-changed-my-career-pragmatic-thinking-and-learning.html#why-this-book&quot;&gt;brains works in that way&lt;/a&gt; and probably everyone experienced that feeling in the past. This is the easiest way to enable &lt;em&gt;rich mode&lt;/em&gt; in our brains, because we are switching perspective and way of thinking about the problem. It does not have to be an actual &lt;em&gt;rubber duck&lt;/em&gt;, it can be another person in the office or even a &lt;em&gt;LEGO&lt;/em&gt; minifigure. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_Demeter&quot;&gt;Law of Demeter&lt;/a&gt; - This the most underestimated law from that book. Someone said that it is applicable to the &lt;em&gt;OOP&lt;/em&gt; only, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?LawOfDemeterRevisited&quot;&gt;it is not true&lt;/a&gt;. Violations of that rule results in many different forms, the lightest and most famous one is probably a &lt;a href=&quot;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?TrainWreck&quot;&gt;train wreck&lt;/a&gt;. I strongly recommend to read this chapter again, mindfully - try to make notes or rethink it in the back of your head. It really helps to understand and shed new light on the meaning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is your favorite advice from that book? Please, share your choice and explanation in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to cover another classical position on my bookshelf, which is very underestimated by the community. Recently, it receives proper respect, even the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/unclebobmartin&quot;&gt;Uncle Bob&lt;/a&gt; recommends to read it. Book covers functional programming in an &lt;em&gt;exotic&lt;/em&gt; language, but each &lt;em&gt;MIT&lt;/em&gt; freshman have to read it and they can do it easily. It is possible thanks to the three brilliant authors who created a very comprehensible and timeless book (which is, in my opinion, even more actual now). Stay tuned to the next post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pragprog.com/book/tpp/the-pragmatic-programmer&quot;&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer, The Pragmatic Bookshelf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/books-that-changed-my-career/2015/04/12/books-that-changed-my-career-the-pragmatic-programmer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/books-that-changed-my-career/2015/04/12/books-that-changed-my-career-the-pragmatic-programmer.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Books that changed my career - Pragmatic Thinking and Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;books-that-changed-my-career---pragmatic-thinking-and-learning&quot;&gt;Books that changed my career - Pragmatic Thinking and Learning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;quote class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;This blog post is the second in the series which contains the most influential books that I have read in my programming career. This is my private ranking, each post contains a good dose of my private opinions (you have been warned &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;), but besides that I hope that you will find it valuable.&lt;/quote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming and designing is very thankful activity, when everything snaps and clicks together (programmers call this state &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;). Nevertheless, it can be extremely frustrating as well, especially when you try to solve something really difficult, or you are overloaded with work, maybe personal issues. Sometimes the same hard problem will be solved in a day, sometimes it will take couple of weeks instead (and I am assuming doing it in both cases from scratch and for the first time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some people seem to be more effective than others at first sight. Like they do not have &lt;em&gt;bad days&lt;/em&gt; at all. This can be observed especially in larger teams, for longer periods of time - when you can work with multiple colleagues several times, where each activity is separated by a few weeks. I am not a huge fan of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biorhythm&quot;&gt;biorythm&lt;/a&gt; pseudoscience, so there must be a different explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases they have got &lt;em&gt;very good habits&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;huge self-awareness&lt;/em&gt;. This sounds almost like an obvious statement, but actually it is not so simple to bring it to your daily working environment. We are learning all the time (and someone who stops learning as an active programmer, while acting like an expert, has treated himself with &lt;quote&gt;&lt;i&gt;the professional kiss of death&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;) and it could be useful to know all science and these little tricks which will ease and improve the whole process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, someone has collected many of good techniques and advice in a book, with an addition of the science (&lt;em&gt;neuroscience&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;psychology&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cognitive science&lt;/em&gt;) necessary to explain everything in greater detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pragmatic Thinking and Learning: Refactor Your Wetware&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Programming Thinking and Learning&quot; src=&quot;/assets/PragmaticThinkingAndLearning.jpg&quot; class=&quot;book&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-this-book&quot;&gt;Why this book?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not a surprise that this person is &lt;em&gt;Andy Hunt&lt;/em&gt;, one of &lt;em&gt;pragmatic programmers&lt;/em&gt;. The first thing that (I hope &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;) caught your attention is a &lt;em&gt;subtitle&lt;/em&gt;. It has a subtle pun - the word &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetware_(brain)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;wetware&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I encourage you to dig deeper into the meaning of this word, because it is crucial to rewire your thinking to a proper attitude, necessary to work with this book effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is structured in a very deliberate way, we are starting with definitions and theoretical introduction to the learning process (&lt;em&gt;Dreyfus Skill Acquisition&lt;/em&gt; model). Then we are digging deeper into mechanisms that are working inside our brains, with a small dose of inevitable theory. After knowing how your brain works &lt;em&gt;inside out&lt;/em&gt;, we are ready to rewire and refactor our &lt;em&gt;wetware&lt;/em&gt; - we will try to overcome our primal instincts (&lt;quote&gt;&lt;i&gt;I am the evolved one&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;), we will try to learn deliberately, work in a focused manner. At the end author introduces the key concepts how be an expert, but still be a passionate and eager to learn even more. If you met &lt;em&gt;Dreyfus Model&lt;/em&gt; before, the whole structure will look similar for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides science, the book also introduces many well-known and verified methods like &lt;em&gt;GTD&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Getting_Things_Done&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/a&gt;), positive psychology or techniques known from &lt;em&gt;Agile&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;eXtreme Programming&lt;/em&gt;. Even referrals to the classical &lt;em&gt;Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/em&gt; book are used in a proper context (e.g. &lt;em&gt;rubber duck debugging&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;boiling frog&lt;/em&gt; explanation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As engineers, we are rather skeptical in terms of emotions, instincts and psychology. This cannot be described, evaluated and verified with any mathematical or physical model that we know. It looks to us as &lt;em&gt;voodoo&lt;/em&gt;, a kind of black magic which involves too many irrational things at once. But this book is different, the major advantage is that is written in a &lt;em&gt;geek&lt;/em&gt; language for geeks, by a &lt;em&gt;computer geek&lt;/em&gt;. And moreover you will experience only fully scientific explanations to the certain behaviors (supported by real studies, everything referenced in book contents or annotations). Even the chapter describing &lt;em&gt;meditation&lt;/em&gt; techniques, which at the first sight definitely is not supported by any science, has some reasonable explanations based on research related to &lt;em&gt;breathing techniques&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, many of these techniques are not a silver bullet for everyone, but I strongly suggest at least trying them. Do not rush through the book, even the author encourages slower reading and thinking about the chapter currently being read (and he does it by introducing small exercises which require e.g. walking or drawing &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;). If you feel that a certain technique is not for you, it is fine - &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me the most important and &lt;em&gt;eye opening&lt;/em&gt; techniques are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Learning and experiencing with all senses&lt;/i&gt; - I was a huge believer in the theory that people learn with some senses better, which turns out not to be true. You should learn and experience using as many senses and techniques as you can (it enables more areas in your brain). Try to scribble and listen during meetings, try acting, role play during planning - it brings new solutions and creative ways to the table.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Deliberate scribbling&lt;/i&gt; - I have done this in the past, but I have stopped (because I thought that noting everything digitally will much better). That was a wrong move - you can see above why, but that’s the immediate thing that brings value after doing it one or two times. I just feel more focused and I can see visually the actual problem and solution in my head. I will never stop doing that again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Morning Text Dump&lt;/i&gt; - Another &lt;em&gt;eye opening&lt;/em&gt; technique. It may sounds funny at the beginning, but the first thing you should do after waking up is not a coffee, but a morning text dump. You should literally write 2-3 pages of text, just after out of the bed - the things that you actually remember. After couple of days you will be able to &lt;em&gt;dump&lt;/em&gt; almost anything that is in the back of your head (processed by the &lt;em&gt;rich mode&lt;/em&gt; of your brain).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myers%E2%80%93Briggs_Type_Indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Myers-Briggs Type Indicator&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - I strongly recommend to read about this and take a test. Results can be ground breaking for you, but even if they will acknowledge what you already know, the original test has some advice and explanations why with type of your personality some things can be hard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lizard Brain&lt;/i&gt; - Very important knowledge, especially if you are a very &lt;em&gt;impulsive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;judging&lt;/em&gt; type. It is the root cause of almost all problems related to subconscious, compulsive behaviors that you may express, especially if you are dealing with huge stress or deadlines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oblique_Strategies&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Oblique Statements&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - For me that was the strangest one, but I gave it a try and the results also amazed me. I suggest you to try it by yourself, it is astonishing to see what your brain can deduce, in your actual context from, at the very first sight, words cluster (because they sound and look like this sometimes &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:stuck_out_tongue:&quot; alt=&quot;:stuck_out_tongue:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f61b.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware that I have started this series with less obvious positions in the programmer’s library. For the next review, I would like to shift a little bit - to the more standard and established books. This is a classical one, again from the &lt;em&gt;Pragmatic Programmers&lt;/em&gt; sign. I have three copies of this book: in English (as an &lt;em&gt;ebook&lt;/em&gt;), in Polish (again, as an ebook), but the most valuable for me is the printed Polish version, which I have received from my friend, with an inscription. Stay tuned! &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning&quot;&gt;Pragmatic Thinking and Learning, The Pragmatic Bookshelf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/books-that-changed-my-career/2015/03/07/books-that-changed-my-career-pragmatic-thinking-and-learning.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/books-that-changed-my-career/2015/03/07/books-that-changed-my-career-pragmatic-thinking-and-learning.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
