<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>afronski.pl - Tag: conferences</title>
    <description>Random thoughts from top of my head - afronski.pl</description>
    <link>http://www.afronski.pl</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.afronski.pl/tag/conferences/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>My picks of NDC 2014 - part I</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-picks-of-ndc-2014---part-i&quot;&gt;My picks of NDC 2014 - part I&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97329157&quot;&gt;Kevlin Henney - Seven Ineffective Coding Habits of Many Programmers&lt;/a&gt; - Very refreshing talk about style and programming habbits. Even if it has many controversial points from your perspective and it is very opinionated, many of them are at least thought-provoking and maybe they should be reconsidered and rethought again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97315946&quot;&gt;Hadi Hariri - Developing in a Decade&lt;/a&gt; - Very inspiring and refreshing talk what software development, internet and whole IT actually is and why it should change if we want to be happier and live in the better world. Amazing anegdotes and very thought-provoking comparisons to the books (Orwell’s &lt;em&gt;“1984”&lt;/em&gt;, Huxley’s &lt;em&gt;“Brave New World”&lt;/em&gt;, Postman’s &lt;em&gt;“Amusing Ourselves to Death”&lt;/em&gt;). For me, this is the best presentation of this year NDC by now.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97530863&quot;&gt;Robert C. Martin - Clean Architecture and Design&lt;/a&gt; - Strongly recommended if you have not seen earlier talks made by &lt;em&gt;Uncle Bob&lt;/em&gt; related with this topic. The most appropriate summary of this talk: &lt;em&gt;application’s business rules are the most important things, protect them - everything is a implementation detail and it should be pluggable&lt;/em&gt;. In other words &lt;em&gt;good architecture maximizes the number of decisions not made&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97505656&quot;&gt;Tim Berglund - Discrete Math You Need to Know&lt;/a&gt; - Inspiring talk (even if you may think that math cannot be inspiring). Definitely recommended, at first - it is recommended to stretch your mind frequently, moreover - it is nice to know more and have these tools in your toolbox (or what is even more recommended - refresh it). Surprisingly, still many people in IT do not know how the RSA works underneath.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97318800&quot;&gt;Denise R. Jackobs - Banish Your Inner Critic&lt;/a&gt; - It can be very enlightening talk for many people, maybe even a life changer. If you have problems with pursuing to the perfection state, procrastination and you have feeling and knowledge that you are a victim of &lt;em&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/em&gt; definitely worth watching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97516288&quot;&gt;Robert C. Martin - Advanced Test Driven Development&lt;/a&gt; - Again, if you have seen it before, there is probably nothing new, but if not - please definitely watch it. Very interesting concept called &lt;em&gt;transformation priority premise&lt;/em&gt;. And surprising summary - &lt;em&gt;if statement is a degenerated case of while loop&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97537026&quot;&gt;Scott Bellware - TDD in Tatters&lt;/a&gt; - Eye-opening introduction about cognitive theory and learning. Very nice differentiation between crude and subtle things, which sometimes fells out and disappear in the process of learning. I disagree about that automation leads to removal a connection between the programmers and code, but still it is a viable talk (at least the beginning about &lt;em&gt;amateur cognitive theory&lt;/em&gt;, pointing out the subtleties and explaining the design role in &lt;em&gt;TDD&lt;/em&gt; acronym). The most important quote from this presentation is &lt;em&gt;every test is an additional coupling to the code&lt;/em&gt; - and by providing good design we should minimize the coupling, we should control it. It is the subtle thing that we often ignore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-watch-these-videos-offline&quot;&gt;How to watch these videos offline?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, since 2013 there are no &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;torrent&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; files, which combine all videos in one place. But there is a solution - we can use &lt;code&gt;Selenium&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;JavaScript&lt;/em&gt; driver to scrap all links from &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;HTML5&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;video&lt;/em&gt; tags. Complete source code of scripts and helpers is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/afronski/playground-repository/tree/master/vimeo-scraper&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Installation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# On Arch Linux, Selenium Chrome WebDriver is available only in AUR.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; ~ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;pacaur -S chromedriver
&lt;span class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; ~ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;npm install
&lt;span class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; ~ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;node vimeo-scraper.js &amp;gt; urls.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the output file you will receive list of URLs which point directly to &lt;em&gt;MP4&lt;/em&gt; ready to download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix---a-bitter-state-of-headless-browsers&quot;&gt;Appendix - A bitter state of headless browsers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that there are tools capable to do such things headlessly. I thought that it will be an easy task to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I have tested &lt;code&gt;Phantom.js&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;SlimmerJS&lt;/code&gt; (representatives of two major browser engines - &lt;em&gt;WebKit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gecko&lt;/em&gt;) and both does not work (even if creators of &lt;code&gt;SlimmerJS&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://slimerjs.org/features.html&quot;&gt;claims&lt;/a&gt; that it should work with &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;HTML5&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;video&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Phantom.js&lt;/code&gt; is slightly better in this matter - it &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ariya/phantomjs/wiki/Supported-Web-Standards#unsupported-features&quot;&gt;officially&lt;/a&gt; does not support &lt;em&gt;audio&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;video&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best implementation of &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;WebKit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; rendering engine available to Node.js called &lt;em&gt;Chimera&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/deanmao/node-chimera/issues/44#issuecomment-30561620&quot;&gt;no longer maintained&lt;/a&gt;. It was a very nice module, I have used it in the past - very unfortunate and disappointing decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you really want to scrape pages headlessly by doing more than simple rendering, measure loading time and capture a single screenshot, you need to use the good, old and reliable pair: &lt;code&gt;Selenium&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Xvfb&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/channels/ndc2014&quot;&gt;NDC 2014 Vimeo Playlist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://slimmerjs.org&quot;&gt;SlimmerJS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phantomjs.org&quot;&gt;phantomjs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/deanmao/node-chimera&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;node-chimera&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 22:10:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/2014/06/16/my-picks-of-NDC-2014-part-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/2014/06/16/my-picks-of-NDC-2014-part-1.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My picks of NDC 2014 - part II</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-picks-of-ndc-2014---part-ii&quot;&gt;My picks of NDC 2014 - part II&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another presentations worth looking from the past NDC conference (previous part is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.afronski.pl/2014/06/16/my-picks-of-NDC-2014-part-1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97537675&quot;&gt;Venkat Subramaniam - Towards an Evolutionary Architecture&lt;/a&gt; - Very nice talk which summarizes all necessary things which are important in the concept of &lt;em&gt;Good Architecture&lt;/em&gt;. An architect in Agile have been considered as obsolete by many people, but actually it is the opposite. Good architecture defers decisions, enables evolution and moreover handles or even removes completely the complexity. Besides that - a very nice Agile approach is to prioritize features and assignments by the business value and the architectural impact - by doing that you can really avoid many pitfalls when you are moving forward and crush the knowledge during the process of building the application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97415346&quot;&gt;Cory House - Becoming an Outlier: Career Reboot for the Developer Mind&lt;/a&gt; - Definitely recommended video to watch. For many people it will be a mind and eye opening experience. Handful of valuable thoughts and advices how to manage your career, change your habits and adapt in the continuously changing environment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97516289&quot;&gt;Roy Osherove - Beautiful Builds&lt;/a&gt; - Very refreshing talk. It starts by very obvious, but very often forgotten statement that &lt;em&gt;automated builds are not the continuous integration&lt;/em&gt;. It introduces important concept of &lt;em&gt;shipping skeleton&lt;/em&gt;. Mixing operational knowledge with building and deployment knowledge is also an anti-pattern. Talk contains a very useful set of patterns and best practices about CI and even Continuous Deployment - definitely recommended.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97507576&quot;&gt;Doc Norton - The Technical Debt Trap&lt;/a&gt; - Very wise and mindful explanation of Technical Debt metaphor (and moreover - the good and only true one). If you are operating this metaphor and you often use it, please watch this presentation and be sure that all points which are related with the true definition are fulfilled. Because if not, you are talking about &lt;em&gt;cruft&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;debt&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97408239&quot;&gt;Joe Armstrong - The mess we’re in&lt;/a&gt; - In most cases talks presented by Joe Armstrong can look like a little spontaneous, sometimes even unprepared. However it is a false belief - amount of experience, insight, pragmatic and at the same time scientific approach to the computing can be really underestimated. Knowledge and very insightful anecdotes are &lt;em&gt;flowing out this talk&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to know more or you are merely interested about the history of computing and how it actually will affect the future of computer science, it is a must-watch presentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97505679&quot;&gt;Aral Balkan - Free is a lie&lt;/a&gt; - Definitely recommended talk, especially if you do not have an idea what is a Google / Facebook business model. For those people it can be even a controversial talk (for me it is because of presenting Mozilla as not a ‘Free’ option in the IT world - claiming that most of the income comes from the Google and only that disqualifies this company from being &lt;em&gt;free as a liberty&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;just unfair&lt;/em&gt;). In other words - if you do not know this already, by using free services - you are not a consumer, you are a product - &lt;em&gt;a data source&lt;/em&gt; - nothing less, nothing more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97541185&quot;&gt;Venkat Subramaniam - Core Software Design Principles&lt;/a&gt; - Worth looking if you forgot or you would like to refresh your knowledge about &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;SOLID&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; principles, or you do not know what &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;YAGNI&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;DRY&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;TDA&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; means. Otherwise, you will watch a rather repetitive (but not boring) presentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97337252&quot;&gt;Garrett Smith - Functional code considered Beautiful&lt;/a&gt; - Definitely worth looking, especially that it is a kind of a rather &lt;em&gt;soft&lt;/em&gt; talk with very pragmatic insights, without &lt;em&gt;preaching&lt;/em&gt; and not necessary &lt;em&gt;marketing&lt;/em&gt;. If you are not convinced enough - try to think about very readable, declarative code which is oriented around concurrency and is side-effect free - how it should look like? And one more - presented sample with &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;GCD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is beautiful and enlightening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97514517&quot;&gt;Mathias Brandewinder - F# and Machine Learning: a winning combination&lt;/a&gt; - Inspiring and fresh talk, both regarding the topic and presented programming language. Definitely worth looking if you are interested in the polyglot programming movement, and if you are looking for interesting language to learn in this or next year. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/97419178&quot;&gt;Bruce Tate - Pipe Dreams&lt;/a&gt; - Another talk from the polyglot programming family. In this case it presents only two key pieces of Elixir, a new language which is a mix of Ruby syntax, Erlang VM and OTP library, but does it well and deeply - actually it is open-minded in terms of specific approach to the data processing paradigm and sequentiality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/2014/08/28/my-picks-of-NDC-2014-part-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/2014/08/28/my-picks-of-NDC-2014-part-2.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The best of Lambda Days 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-best-of-lambda-days-2015&quot;&gt;The best of Lambda Days 2015&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can look with admiration and envy to the US or European based conferences like &lt;a href=&quot;https://thestrangeloop.com/&quot;&gt;Strangeloop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ndc-london.com/&quot;&gt;NDC Oslo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ndc-london.com/&quot;&gt;NDC London&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erlang-factory.com/sfbay2015/home&quot;&gt;Erlang Factory San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;. Thankfully, conferences list in Poland looks better year after year (e.g. amazing &lt;a href=&quot;http://devday.pl/&quot;&gt;DevDay&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyrd.com/2014/euclojure/&quot;&gt;EuroClojure 2014&lt;/a&gt; or incoming &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elixirconf.eu/&quot;&gt;Elixir Conf EU 2015&lt;/a&gt;). Still, I was not aware of fact, that there is a conference dedicated purely to the &lt;em&gt;functional programming&lt;/em&gt;. Thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lechglowiak&quot;&gt;@lechglowiak&lt;/a&gt; I discovered such amazing conference in Kraków (so it is relatively close to the place where I live).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LambdaDaysHeader.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lambda Days 2015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I am talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://lambdadays.org/&quot;&gt;Lambda Days 2015&lt;/a&gt;. Organization, venue and prepared tracks raised the bar high. Great kudos to the organizers for creating such amazing event! I am glad that I could take part in such awesome and inspiring experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I would like to focus on the best presentations which I have seen live. Please note, that list is far from complete. Parallel tracks caused hard choices sometimes. I am still catching up with the rest of the talks, thanks to the uploaded &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/tag:Lambda+Days&quot;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-top-5&quot;&gt;My Top 5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/121374004&quot;&gt;How computers change our brains. Can screen-time cause mental or neurological disorders?&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Kinga Panasiewicz&lt;/em&gt; - Very inspiring and scientific talk about the most precious part of our body - &lt;em&gt;brain&lt;/em&gt;. As people which constantly learns and, what is even more important, we use &lt;em&gt;brain&lt;/em&gt; in our daily work without rest, we should know almost everything about the possible damage and &lt;em&gt;“hygiene”&lt;/em&gt;. I am a little biased, because I love learning about that topics, but I recommend watching it. &lt;strong&gt;Good mental health is a key for effective and stress-less work&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding Cancer Behavior with F# by &lt;em&gt;Evelina Gobasova&lt;/em&gt; - Being a part of such research team can be intimidating, but also rewarding. Your impact as a computer scientist cannot be more meaningful than that. Highly inspiring talk, with many technical details related with &lt;em&gt;F#&lt;/em&gt;. If you are interested in type providers or using functional programming as a data scientist, it is highly recommended to watch it (&lt;em&gt;but it is not uploaded yet&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building systems in Clojure by &lt;em&gt;Matthias Nehlsen&lt;/em&gt; - I am following Matthias blog and work (on his &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/building-a-system-in-clojure&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; and side projects) and I was not disappointed. Presentation described practical approach to the building systems, not only in Clojure, but in general with use of the functional programming language. If you are interested in such details, I recommend to watch this talk (&lt;em&gt;video is not available yet&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/123606435&quot;&gt;State, Communication and Side-Effects in Idris&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Edwin Brady&lt;/em&gt; - I was blown away by features and capabilities of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.idris-lang.org/example/&quot;&gt;Idris&lt;/a&gt;. Literally, this talk just blown my mind - &lt;em&gt;dependent types&lt;/em&gt; looks really promising. Even if someone claims that it is a purely academical thing (but in presented context, it does not look as a purely theoretical work) it is still valuable at least to briefly look at it. Mostly for expanding your horizon and drill your brain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lessons from Erlang VM by &lt;em&gt;Michał Ślaski&lt;/em&gt; - I am a huge fan of &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; ecosystem, mainly because of pragmatism and focus on building &lt;em&gt;reliable&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;resilient&lt;/em&gt;  systems. Moreover, a lot of time we speak how to build such systems and we treat the maintenance part as a &lt;em&gt;side-effect&lt;/em&gt; and something not worth our attention. It should be exactly opposite! Most of the time related with software lifetime is spent in the maintenance phase. We need to build mission critical systems on a solid foundation, with maintenance in mind from the &lt;em&gt;day zero&lt;/em&gt;. Talk recommended for people interested in getting familiar with &lt;em&gt;Erlang VM&lt;/em&gt; features overview, which ease building systems with such requirements (&lt;em&gt;talk video it is not uploaded yet&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stickers-on-participant-badges-and-lambda-academy&quot;&gt;Stickers on participant badges and Lambda Academy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the conference there was an interesting exhibition. I noticed, as probably most of the people, strange sticker on my participant’s badge. It turns out, that one of the stands has &lt;em&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/em&gt; installation with NFC tag reader (yes, it is a NFC-powered sticker). This sent an XMPP message to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.erlang-solutions.com/products/mongooseim-massively-scalable-ejabberd-platform&quot;&gt;MongooseIM&lt;/a&gt; each time when someone scanned a badge. Everything built in Erlang (even the sticker scanner). &lt;strong&gt;Awesome idea!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exhibition was dedicated to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lambdaacademy.org/blog/&quot;&gt;Lambda Academy&lt;/a&gt; initiative. Software used at the conference - chat, voting system (back-end and mobile application) were created in a first iteration of lectures. Whole academy is focused on use &lt;em&gt;functional programming languages&lt;/em&gt; and popularizing them in the community. Feel free to subscribe, in order to receive updates about new initiatives and future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a curious person, this conference is a must-be place for you. If you are an open person, eager to learn new stuff, especially - related with functional programming - go for it! I am looking forward to the Lambda Days 2016. &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:wink:&quot; alt=&quot;:wink:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lambdadays.org&quot;&gt;Lambda Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lambdaacademy.org&quot;&gt;Lambda Academy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 19:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/2015/04/06/the-best-of-lambda-days.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/2015/04/06/the-best-of-lambda-days.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Elixir Conf EU 2015 - Afterthoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;elixir-conf-eu-2015---afterthoughts&quot;&gt;Elixir Conf EU 2015 - Afterthoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.afronski.pl/2015/04/06/the-best-of-lambda-days.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; about interesting events, I have said that more of them will come in future. I have participated in one of these - &lt;em&gt;ElixirConf EU&lt;/em&gt; in Kraków and I must admit - it was the best conference I have ever been since &lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyrd.com/2011/falsy-values/&quot;&gt;Falsy Values in 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the second in the world conference about &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; programming language, it brings almost 200 people interested in that topic to the former Polish capital. Most of people was either from &lt;em&gt;Ruby&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; side and I think that such mixture is a &lt;em&gt;key thing&lt;/em&gt; related to the &lt;em&gt;joy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; of that event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ElixirConfEU2015Header.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elixir Conf EU 2015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talks-and-workshops&quot;&gt;Talks and Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a day before actual conference organizers prepared two workshops - one about &lt;em&gt;Phoenix&lt;/em&gt; framework and one about &lt;em&gt;OTP and Elixir&lt;/em&gt;. I have participated in the second one - it was a really nice experience. Workshop was full of knowledge, I have met interesting people, with very positive attitude, whom are willing to network and share their experiences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual conference days was started and ended with very nice keynotes - each of them was a different experience. We have very nice and thoughtful keynote from Joe Armstrong, which explains many problems related to the programming language design, from the perspective of &lt;em&gt;Elixir’s&lt;/em&gt; older brother - &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt;. Jose Valim presented bright future and interesting details related with &lt;em&gt;Elixir&lt;/em&gt; evolution, and finally Chris had a very nice overview and development plans related with &lt;em&gt;Phoenix&lt;/em&gt; framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I was also impressed by other talks. It was very interesting to see many use cases in which people used that piece of technology. I think that both groups have many valuable opinions and observations. For me, talks made by people with &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; experience were particularly valuable, because they are coming from more mature technology. It is a different background and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atmosphere&quot;&gt;Atmosphere&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to focus on one particular element, which makes this conference so enjoyable - &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. I have never met so many &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;friendly&lt;/em&gt; people. I have wonderful time during networking, countless talks during breaks or lunches. And to sum it up - during lightning talks &lt;em&gt;Jose Valim&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jim Freeze&lt;/em&gt; received a &lt;em&gt;3D printed Elixir logo&lt;/em&gt; designed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hrobeers.github.io/finFoil/&quot;&gt;finFoil&lt;/a&gt; software made by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hrobeers&quot;&gt;@hrobeers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazing community!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center-tweet&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ElixirConfEU&quot;&gt;@ElixirConfEU&lt;/a&gt; Thanks for the great conference. My lightning talk including the Elixir 3D file: &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/m06YLIwA5h&quot;&gt;http://t.co/m06YLIwA5h&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/0VJa9SDN02&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/0VJa9SDN02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Hans Robeers (@hrobeers) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hrobeers/status/591794764351197184&quot;&gt;April 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good choice to invest my time and money in that event. Three days full of &lt;em&gt;energy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; sharing. As a community we have interesting perspectives. We can derive from very experienced and stable &lt;em&gt;Erlang&lt;/em&gt; ecosystem. We have a very nice and promising community, full of amazing and creative people. I will go definitely to the next &lt;em&gt;ElixirConf EU 2016&lt;/em&gt; which take place in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you there! &lt;img class=&quot;emoji&quot; title=&quot;:smile:&quot; alt=&quot;:smile:&quot; src=&quot;https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f604.png&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hrobeers/status/591794764351197184&quot;&gt;Lightning talks and their effect, done by @hrobeers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elixirconf.eu/&quot;&gt;Elixir Conf EU 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.afronski.pl/2015/05/07/elixir-conf-eu-2015-afterthoughts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.afronski.pl/2015/05/07/elixir-conf-eu-2015-afterthoughts.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
